It feels like 100 videos ago that I told you that we were going to have instant gratification with our
첫 프로젝트가 성공하면 바로 만족할 거라고 말한 게 100편
first project, and you'd be within your rights to feel like it hasn't exactly been instant gratification.
전인 것 같은데 그렇게 바로 만족스럽지 않다고 느끼는 건 여러분 권리예요
But never fear, I'm going to make up for it with a nice juicy project to start us off.
하지만 걱정 마세요, 멋진 프로젝트로 만회할 테니까요
So if you already have JupyterLab running like the window up in your browser, please close that.
이미 브라우저의 창처럼 JupyterLab이 돌아가고 있다면 그걸 닫으세요
And if you already had your Anaconda prompt in windows, then exit out of that and close that and start
이미 윈도우에 아나콘다 프롬프트가 있다면 그것을 종료하고 닫았다가 다시 시작하세요
again.
PC와 Mac에 새로운 아나콘다 프롬프트를 불러오고 새로운 터미널을 불러옵니다 모든 걸 닫았어요
everything down because we've made that env file and I want to start from absolute scratch.
저 부럽지 않은 파일을 만들었으니까요 완전히 처음부터 시작하고 싶어요
Go into your projects folder into LM engineering, and you'll remember the first thing.
LM 엔지니어링의 프로젝트 폴더로 가세요 첫 번째 것을 기억하실 거예요
And you'll always have to do this if you come in fresh with a, with or without your Jupyter Lab running,
그리고 항상 이걸 해야 합니다 주피터 랩이 실행 중이건 아니건 콘다를
you type conda activate LMS.
입력해 LMS를 활성화하세요
That is how you activate your environment.
그렇게 환경을 활성화하는 거죠
If you're using virtualenv, then there was a different PC and a mac way of doing it in the readme.
가상env를 사용한다면 리드메에 다른 PC와 맥 방식이 있어요
I do that, and my clue is that the prompt has now changed to LMS.
그렇게 하면 단서는 프롬프트가 LMS로 바뀌었다는 거죠
And for windows people in your Anaconda prompt, it should have done the same thing.
아나콘다 프롬프트에서 윈도우 사람들을 위해 같은 것을 해야 하죠
And now you type the two wonderful words Jupyter Lab.
이제 멋진 두 단어를 입력하세요 주피터 연구소
And when you do that, it thinks for a second and up comes JupyterLab right here.
그렇게 하면 잠시 생각을 하고 주피터랩이 나타나죠
Instant gratification.
즉각적인 만족감이죠
It says.
그렇게 쓰여 있어요
So you may not see this.
못 보실지도 몰라요
Actually, it may come up for you the first time just looking like this.
사실, 이렇게만 봐도 처음 떠오를지도 몰라요
Perhaps this might be more similar to what you're seeing right now.
지금 보시는 것과 비슷할지도 몰라요
So this is Jupyter Lab for some people.
어떤 사람들에게는 여기가 주피터 연구소예요
This is old news.
이건 옛날 뉴스예요
You've probably used this a lot.
많이 써보셨죠?
For some of you, this might be new.
새로운 분들도 계실 거예요
And I'm here to tell you that it is fabulous.
정말 멋지다는 말을 해 주러 왔어요
It is this very interactive way for data scientists to work with code.
데이터 과학자들이 코드로 작업하는 상호작용적인 방법이죠
It's full of some hairy stuff like use global variables a lot in Jupyter Lab.
주피터 랩은 전면 변수를 많이 사용하는 등 아슬아슬한 것으로 가득하죠
And we know, as if you're from an engineering background that that's not not very good behavior, but
공학 전공자로서 봤을 때 좋은 행동은 아니지만 연구 개발의
it's something that we do as part of research and development.
일환으로 하는 일이에요
And so we just do it.
그래서 그냥 했어요
As you will see, it means that you can be very productive as you experiment.
곧 보시겠지만 실험하면서 아주 생산적일 수 있다는 뜻이에요
When we get to week eight, at the end of the course, we're going to be looking at productionizing,
과정의 끝인 8주 차에는 프로덕션화와 우리가 하는 걸 살펴볼 겁니다
the stuff that we do, and we'll be talking about how we migrate from JupyterLab into proper code and
JupyterLab에서 제대로 된 코드와 배포로 마이그레이션하는 방법도 얘기할
deployment and so on.
거고요
But we don't need to worry about that stuff now.
하지만 지금은 그런 걱정 안 해도 돼요
So on the left here, you have something called the File Browser, which is kind of what you would expect
왼쪽에 파일 브라우저라는 게 있어요 사실 기대하시는 거죠
actually, you might have come in like this, of course, which is showing you the parent directory.
이렇게 들어와 부모 디렉토리를 보여주고 있죠
There's a directory for each of the weeks that we'll be going through, and you can see the things we
우리가 검토할 매주 디렉터리가 있어요 리드메이트와 환경에 관해
know about the Readme and the environment.yml here as well.
우리가 아는 걸 볼 수 있죠 yml도 여기 있어요
And without further ado, we're going to go into week one.
그럼 지체 없이 첫째 주를 시작하죠
Now, if this is your first time ever in JupyterLab, I've made a guide to JupyterLab that you can come
주피터랩에 처음 오신 거라면 제가 안내서를 만들어 놨으니
into and look at you.
와서 보세요
Just double click here and it will bring it up, and it will take you on a quick tour of what you need
여길 더블 클릭하면 get이 나옵니다 여러분이 해야 할 일을 간단히 보여줍니다
to do, just so that you get a handle of things.
여러분이 잘 처리할 수 있도록요
For example, you'll learn that you can click in one of these boxes here, which is called a cell.
예를 들어, 여기 있는 상자 중 하나를 클릭할 수 있어요 셀이라고 하죠
You hold down shift.
시동을 꺼요
You press return or enter on your keyboard and it executes it and prints the results for and as you
자판에서 반환이나 입력을 누르면 실행되고 결과를 출력합니다
go through, you scroll down and you go on to do the next thing, and you can just come in and execute
그리고 스크롤을 내리면 다음 작업이 나옵니다 실행하고 볼 수
and see.
있죠
My favorite fruit is bananas, and you can go through and use this guide to Jupiter as a way to learn
제가 제일 좋아하는 과일은 바나나예요 이 주피터 가이드북을 참고해서 주피터 랩을
some of the tricks of using Jupiter Lab, and I hope that will be helpful for you.
사용하는 기술을 배우세요 도움이 되기를 바라요
But I imagine many of the people on this course will have used Jupiter once or twice and will be familiar
하지만 이 항로에 있는 많은 사람이 목성을 한두 번 사용해 봤을 테고 그 경이로움에
with the wonder of it.
익숙할 거예요
And so that brings us to our day one project, which is right here.
이제 첫날 프로젝트 차례입니다 바로 여기요
And again, I've slightly cheekily called it instant gratification.
전 좀 뻔뻔하게도 즉각적인 만족감이라고 했죠
I know you've put in a fair amount of work for this, and day one has been a pretty long day, but it
이 집을 위해 많은 일을 한 거 알아요 첫날은 꽤 긴 하루였지만 그만한 가치가
hopefully will be worth it.
있길 바라요 Put
Uh, there's some spiel here to remind you one more time that I'm here to help.
다시 한번 말하지만 난 도우러 온 거예요
There's my email address.
제 이메일 주소예요
This is my LinkedIn.
이건 제 링크트인이죠
I always love it if people connect with me on LinkedIn.
링크드인에서 사람들이 저와 소통하는 걸 좋아해요
It's nice if you if you put a message there to say hi, but you really don't need to as well.
for 안녕이라는 메시지를 넣는 것도 좋지만 꼭 그럴 필요는 없어요
If you just want to just connect, that's good with me.
그냥 교감만 하고 싶다면 그렇게 하세요
I always will accept connections from people taking this course.
이 수업을 듣는 학생들의 인맥은 언제든 환영이에요
Of course.
물론이죠
The other thing it tells you right here is that there is another notebook.
여기서 또 알 수 있는 건 다른 공책이 있다는 거예요
And sorry, these these Jupyter labs are known as notebooks.
이 주피터 연구소들은 공책이라고 해요
People call them for historical reasons.
역사적인 이유로 그렇게 부르죠
Uh, there's another notebook here called troubleshooting.
문제 해결이라는 공책이 하나 더 있어요
And troubleshooting is where you will go if you have any problems troubleshooting over here.
문제 해결은 여러분이 여기서 문제를 해결하는 곳이죠
Uh, begins.
시작이죠
Oh, dear.
어떡해요
Uh, has step by step to go through and figure out exactly what's going wrong and check your env file.
단계별로 뭐가 잘못됐는지 파악하고 부럽지 않은 파일을 확인하죠
Looks good.
맛있어 보여요
I check everything as we go through it.
모든 걸 확인하면서 진행해요
So if any troubles at all, you go to troubleshooting and we'll have it sorted.
문제가 생기면 해결을 하면 됩니다. 우리가 해결할게요.
But otherwise we're starting with the day one notebook.
하지만 그렇지 않으면 첫날의 공책부터 시작해야죠
Generally during this course, we'll have a separate notebook for each day so that you can go through
이 과정에서는 매일 따로 노트를 준비합니다 그날의
and learn from that day and do the exercises.
경험을 훑어보며 연습할 수 있죠
Okay.
네
So the first thing we start with is some imports.
우선 수입품부터 살펴볼게요
I often like to put the imports at the top.
전 수입품을 상위권에 두는 걸 좋아해요 Put it up Put it
You have to execute the code in JupyterLab from the top downwards, and we'll start by clicking in this
주피터랩에서 코드를 실행해야 합니다 위에서부터요 이 임포트 셀을 클릭하는 것으로
import cell.
시작하죠
Hold down shift.
기어를 낮추세요
Press return.
회신을 누르세요
And that runs.
잘 달리네요
If this gives you an error, then head over to the troubleshooting notebook.
에러가 발생하면 문제 해결 노트북으로 가세요. HDPULL GAME
I'll tell you what's probably happening, what's going on, and what you need to do about it.
어떤 일이 벌어질지 어떻게 해야 할지 알려줄게요
Most likely is that for some reason, the conda environment isn't activated.
콘다 환경이 활성화되지 않는 게 가장 큰 이유죠
And I'll tell you what to do about that.
어떻게 할지 알려줄게요
Okay.
네
The next thing we're going to do is connect to OpenAI.
다음으로 오픈AI에 연결할 거예요
So this is where we are going to to make our connection to the OpenAI API service so that we can make
여기서 오픈AI API 서비스에 연결할 겁니다 프론티어 모델인 GPT에
a call to GPT, the frontier model and and ask it questions.
전화를 걸어 질문을 할 수 있도록요
Now, of course, we're going to be talking a lot more about OpenAI and GPT and what all these things
오픈AI와 GPT에 대해 더 자세히 이야기할 텐데요
mean.
Get it의 맛을 내는 거죠
Right now, this is just our first lab.
지금은 첫 실험실이에요
So the first thing we do is call something called load dot env.
가장 먼저 로드.Infsi라는 걸 호출해요
And that looks at the dot env file and loads in our secrets.
.Infile을 보고 비밀을 로드하죠
Right now we have one secret the OpenAI API key.
오픈AI API 키라는 비밀이 있어요
And we're going to load that in and put it in a variable called API key.
그걸 로드해 API 키라는 변수에 넣을 거예요 Put it
And we're going to check that it looks decent.
잘 나왔는지 확인해 보죠
It says API key found and looks good so far.
API 키를 찾았고 지금까지는 괜찮아 보이네요
If it doesn't say that.
그렇게 안 쓰여 있다면요
If it doesn't say.
안 적혀 있으면요
API key found and looks good so far, head over to troubleshooting.
API 키를 찾았고 지금까지는 좋습니다. 문제 해결로 가보세요. HDP, HDP.M.
We'll sort it out or.
우리가 해결할게요
Email me uh, LinkedIn with me.
제 이메일로 링크트인을 보내주세요
We'll fix it okay.
우리가 고칠게요
The next thing we do is this simple thing here.
다음 할 일은 간단한 거예요
We take OpenAI.
오픈아이를 점령하죠
We we create an instance of it and put it in OpenAI.
인스턴스를 생성해 OpenAI에 넣죠
Uh, this is where we're.
여기가 우리 집이에요
Actually making the connection to OpenAI done.
오픈라이와의 연결을 완료했어요
All right.
좋아요
So what is this project going to be about today?
오늘 이 프로젝트는 어떤 건가요?
What what business problem are we actually going.
어떤 사업상의 문제를 다루고 있나요?
To solve?
해결요?
It's going to be really simple and actually quite cool.
아주 간단하고 사실 꽤 멋질 거예요
We're going to write a program which is going to be able to look at any web page on the internet, scrape
프로그램을 만들어서 인터넷상의 모든 웹 페이지를 살펴보고 그 내용을 긁어내서
the contents of the web page and then summarize it and present back a short summary of that web page.
요약하고 그 웹 페이지의 짧은 요약을 보여드릴 거예요
You can think of it like you're building your own little web browser, which is like a summarizing web
작은 웹 브라우저를 만든다고 생각해 보세요 웹 브라우저 요약
browser.
같은 거죠
Uh, you know, the Reader's Digest.
리더스 다이제스트 알죠?
It's like a Reader's Digest web browser.
라이더스 다이제스트 웹 브라우저 같아요
Um, that's what we're going to do.
그게 우리가 할 일이에요
That's going to be the project.
그게 프로젝트가 될 거예요
And we're going to start by defining a class, a class website, and which is going to be a very simple
클래스를 정의하는 것으로 시작할게요 클래스 웹사이트요 아주 간단한 유틸리티 클래스가 될
utility class that will represent a website that we've scraped.
겁니다 우리가 긁어모은 웹사이트를 나타내는 거죠
Uh, it's going to be a class which, which will have a URL, a title and a text.
클래스가 될 거예요 URL과 제목, 텍스트가 있는 클래스요
I'm not going to go through this line by line, because you'll be able to read this yourself and get
한 줄씩 살펴보진 않겠습니다 여러분이 직접 읽어보시고
a sense for it as you come through and execute this right after this, uh, and we'll have other labs
바로 실행하실 때 감을 잡으실 수 있을 테니까요 get it 이후엔 다른 랩에서 더 자세히
where we'll go into much more detail on what's going on.
살펴볼 거예요
This is just about your first your first experience with it.
처음 경험하는 거잖아요 그렇죠
Now in this, uh, in the constructor and where I set up this class, I use a package called Beautifulsoup,
생성자에서 이 클래스를 설정했던 곳에서 뷰티풀소우프라는 패키지를 사용했어요
which again, I imagine many of you have come across at some point.
많은 분들이 언젠가 경험하셨을 거예요
It's a fabulous little package that's used for parsing web pages and people who do web scraping, uh,
웹 페이지 파싱에 사용되는 멋진 패키지예요 웹 스크래핑을 하는 사람들은
on a regular basis, like myself, know Beautifulsoup very well indeed.
저처럼 정기적으로 뷰티풀 슈프를 잘 알죠
Uh, and you can use Beautifulsoup to do things like pluck out the title of a web page and get rid of
뷰티풀 get을 이용해서 웹 페이지의 타이틀을 제거하고 스크립트와
things like scripts and style and images and inputs from a web page and then figure out its text.
스타일, 이미지 입력을 제거하고 텍스트를 알아낼 수 있어요
So that is what we're going to do with our, uh, um, uh, class website.
그래서 우리 클래스 웹사이트로 그걸 할 거예요
And then what we're going to do finally is try one out.
마지막으로 한 번 시험해 보죠
So we're going to create a new website object.
새 웹사이트 객체를 생성할게요
And I'm going to pass in this particular website for thoroughly undesirable website happens to be my
이 특정 웹사이트를 넘기겠습니다 철저히 바람직하지 않은 웹사이트가 제 웹사이트가
website.
된 거죠
Uh, and it's a very vanilla website.
웹사이트도 아주 평범해요
But we'll create a class to represent it.
하지만 그걸 대표할 클래스를 만들 거예요
Uh, we'll look at its title and look at the text on the website.
제목과 웹 사이트의 텍스트를 보죠
Let's see if this works.
이게 통할지 보죠
Yes it works.
네, 작동해요
And here we go.
자, 보세요
We're seeing the name of the website.
웹사이트 이름이 보이네요
Uh, and there is something about what's going on on that website right there.
그 웹사이트에 뭔가 일어나고 있어요
Uh, this is just the contents looking a bit scrappy because it's of course, the contents of that web
음, 비트가 좀 허술해 보이네요. 이미지와 자바스크립트
page with images, JavaScript stylesheets all removed.
스타일시트가 모두 삭제되었기 때문이죠.
Okay, so far we've not done anything to do with generative AI or Llms.
지금까지는 재생 인공지능이나 LAM을 사용하지 않았어요
That's coming right up, and we're going to get to it in the next video.
Get in get이 곧 나올 겁니다 다음 비디오에서 알아보죠